Abraham J. Feldman Collection 0012.001.005e
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
Rabbi Abraham J. Feldman
1000
0012.001.005e
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
1.0 Cubic feet 4 Boxes
Abraham Jehiel Feldman, born in 1893 in Kiev, was one of the leading Reform rabbis in the country. He came to the New York in 1906 and received his ordination in 1918 from Hebrew Union College. He was invited to return to New York where he served for almost two years under Rabbi Stephen S. Wise. Following that, Feldman became the assistant of Joseph Krauskopf for five years at his congregation in Philadelphia. In an oral history recorded in 1974, Rabbi Feldman commented on the influences he received from serving under two extremely prominent rabbis who were so different in approach. From Wise, he learned to use the pulpit as a "completely free forum" to espouse his views without control from the congregation. Under Krauskopf, he learned skills for building and maintaining a congregation. Feldman was selected in 1925 to lead at Beth Israel in Hartford. From his boyhood, Feldman was an ardent Zionist, and he spoke out on the matter from the Beth Israel pulpit to his decidedly non-Zionist congregation. During the next few decades, Feldman was unable to convert many of his congregants to Zionism, but he did neutralize opinion and prevent them from joining anti-Zionist groups. He also played a leading role in changing the general attitude among Reform leaders nationally. Feldman acquired a national reputation as a major leader of Reform Judaism and served on the Board of the Hebrew Union College, the Executive Council of the Union of American Hebrew Congregations, and as President of the Central Conference of American Rabbis. He retired in 1968 but continued serving as Rabbi Emeritus until his death in 1977. Rabbi Feldman was also very active in the local secular community. He served as Chaplain to the Connecticut State Guard, the Connecticut State Police, and the Veterans' Hospital. Feldman was involved with various other governmental agencies including the local Selective Service Re-employment Board, the National Recovery Administration in Connecticut, and Department of Defense post-war missions to the Pacific Rim. He was active in inter-faith activities that included the Connecticut Advisory Committee of the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights, lectures at the Hartford Seminary, and the founding of the Hartford Inter-Faith Committee. Rabbi Feldman was a prolific writer of numerous books and articles. He also co-founded the Jewish Ledger in 1929 and edited it for 48 years. In addition, Feldman was a member of the Publications Committee of the Jewish Publication Society, on the Executive Board of the Jewish Book Council of America, and a contributing editor of several Jewish encyclopedias. This is far too small a collection to provide an in-depth look at Rabbi Feldman's life and profession, but, together with material in the Beth Israel Collection, it provides insight into his relationship with the non-Jewish community.
Feldman, Abraham J., Rabbi, b.1893, Ukraine, Russia; Congregation Beth Israel; Oral History; Zionism
- Series I: Records & Manuscripts
  - Awards and Honors / Hartt College of Music Honorary Degree, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Awards and Honors / Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
  - Awards and Honors / Synagogue Council of America, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Biographical, undated (Box 1)
  - Civic Activities, undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1)
  - Inter-faith Activities, undated (Box 1)
  - Inter-faith Activities / Course Taught at St. Joseph College, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts / "How Shall We Be 'Saved'?", undated (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts / "Is Life a Succession of Predetermined Events?", undated (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts / "My Father … My God", undated (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts / "Relationship of the Jewish People and their Religion", undated (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts / "Sin, Repentance and Forgiveness", undated (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts / "What about the Messiah?", undated (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts / "Zionism -- Then and Now", undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
  - Obituaries, undated (Box 1)
  - Oral History Tape Transcript / 1972 Interview for JHSGH (Box 1)
  - Oral History Tape Transcript / 1974 Interview Re: Rabbi Joseph Krauskopf (Box 1)
  - Professional Activities, undated (Box 1)
  - Professional Activities / Central Conference of American Rabbis, Presidency, 1947-1948 (Box 1)
  - Travel / East Asia, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Zionism, undated (Box 1)
- Series III & IV
  - Found in collections, need additional processing, contains Rabbi's messages, correspondence, and speeches, undated (Box 3)
  - Feldman, Helen Block:, undated (Box 3)
  - Obituaries, undated (Box 3)
- Photographs:
  - See: Photographs / People / Feldman, Abraham J., undated
  - See: Photographs / Synagogues / Beth Israel, undated
- Oral Histories:
  - 1972 interview by Bert Gaster for the JHSGH
  - 1974 interview by John Sutherland for Temple University
- Series II: Publications
  - Publications/America and the Jew, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Publications/Another rabbi quits: what does it mean?, 1930 (Box 2)
  - Publications/Being religious today, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Publications/Changing Functions of the Synagogue and the Rabbi,, no date, undated (Box 2)
  - Publications/Choice passages in the Holy Scriptures: A Teacher's Guide, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Publications/Come now let us reason together, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Publications/Concept of Immortality in Judaism, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Publications/Faith of a regular Jew, 1931 (Box 2)
  - Publications/Glory of the imperfect, 1930 (Box 2)
  - Publications/Greatest romance in history, 1930 (Box 2)
  - Publications/I accept, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Publications/I remember, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Publications/If I were a Christian: a Lenten sermon, 1934 (Box 2)
  - Publications/In time of need, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Publications/Israel's flag is not mine, 1949 (Box 2)
  - Publications/Lights and Shadows, 1928 (Box 2)
  - Publications/Lost word, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Publications/Mine Eyes have seen the glory, n.d., undated (Box 2)
  - Publications/Modern Synagogue: a description of Temple Beth Israel, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Publications/New year - Wherein new? 1929 (Box 2)
  - Publications/Reform Judaism, 1956 (Box 2)
  - Publications/The church and clergy in politics, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Publications/The president's message to the 60th annual convention of the central conference of American Rabbis, 1949, undated (Box 2)
  - Publications/We Jews, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Publications/What is faith, 1930 (Box 2)
  - Publications/Why I am a Zionist, 1945 (Box 2)
  - Publications/Why Jews do not accept the Christ, nd, undated (Box 2)
  - Publications/, undated (Box 2)
  - Publications/, undated (Box 2)
  - Publications/, undated (Box 2)